Register of the Robert Allen Griffin Papers, 1942-1971
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Allen Griffin Papers,
1942-1971
75027
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes, 3 envelopes (5.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, speeches and writings, photographs, and printed matter, relating to American technical and economic assistance missions to China and Southeast Asia.
Griffin, R. Allen (Robert Allen), 1893-1981
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical List
1893, September 27 Born, Kansas City, Missouri
1917 B. A., Stanford University
1917-1919 Military service
1919 Reporter, Portland Oregonian and Portland Journal, Portland, Oregon
1919-1920 Secretary to First Polish Minister to U.S., Prince Lubormirski
1920-1921 Director, Polish Bureau of Information
1921 Manager, American Polish Chamber of Commerce
1922 Founder and publisher, Monterey Peninsula Herald, Monterey, California
1935 Founder of radio station, KDON, Del Monte, California
1941-1945 Military service
1942 Co-author, The School of the Citizen Soldier
1948-1949 Deputy Chief, U.S. Economic Cooperation Administration, China
1950 Chief, U.S. Department of State Economic Mission to Southeast Asia
1950-1951 Director, U.S. Economic Cooperation Admnistration, Far East Program Division
1951-1952 Special Representative of the Far East, U.S. Economic Cooperation Administration and Mutual Security Agency
Lapham, Roger Dearborn, 1883-1966.; United States. Dept. of State.; United States. Economic Cooperation Administration.; Asia, Southeastern.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; China.; Economic assistance, American--Asia, Southeastern.; Economic assistance, American--China.; Indochina--History.; Indochina.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--China.; Technical assistance, American--Asia, Southeastern.; Technical assistance, American--China.; United States--Foreign relations.; Vietnam--History.; Vietnam.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1942-1971 (Box 1)
  Arrangement Statement
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Unidentified, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Badger, Vice Admiral Oscar, 1949
  - Baker, John Earl, 1949
  - Bissell, Richard M., Jr., 1951
  - Bolling, Major General A. R., 1948
  - Bramblett, Ernest K., 1951
  - Butterworth, W. Walton, 1950
  - Caldwell, J. Alexander, 1971
  - Chang, C. C., 1949
  - Chennault, Major General Claire E., 1948
  - Chiang Mon-lin, 1949
  - Clay, Eugene H., 1952
  - Cleveland, Harlan, 1948-1949
  - Cline, Howard M., 1952
  - Cochran, Ambassador H. Merle, 1950
  - Coombe, Reginald G., 1949
  - Cooney, P. S., n.d.
  - Davis, Ritchie G., 1948
  - Eldridge, Fred L., 1948-1949
  - Fishel, Wesley R., 1966
  - Flegel, Austin, 1952
  - Foster, William C., n.d.
  - Gould, Dorothy, (Mrs. Randall), 1948
  - Gould, Randall, 1948
  - Hayes, Samuel P., 1968
  - Hoffman, Paul G., 1949
  - Hopkins, Paul S., 1949
  - Hopkins, Peter S., 1949
  - Jessup, Ambassador at Large, Philip C., 1949
  - Josselyn, Windsor, 1948
  - Keswick, John, 1949
  - Knowland, Senator William F., 1948-1949
  - Lapham, Roger D., 1948-1950
  - Lear, Lieutenant General Ben, 1942-1945
  - Li Ming, 1949-1956
  - Little, L. K., 1948-1950
  - McAfee, William, n.d.
  - McCune, Shannon, 1952-1955
  - Mack, Harold L., 1948
  - Meiklejohn, Norman, 1949
  - Merchant, Livingston T., 1949-1961
  - Morin, Relman, 1948
  - Morris, Frances, 1952
  - Moyer, Raymond T., 1953-1960
  - O'Donnell, William, 1948-1949
  - Price, Harry B., 1954-1955
  - Rusk, Dean, 1961
  - Sae Woon Chang, 1952
  - St. Louis, George, 1950
  - Samson, Henry T., 1948-1949
  - Savoy, Willard W., 1952
  - Shen, H. J., 1949
  - Simpson, Roy, 1952
  - Spruance, Admiral Raymond A., 1952
  - Stuart, Ambassador J. Leighton, 1949
  - Sumner, John D., 1949
  - Symington, Charles J., 1951
  - Throp, Colonel Elliot W., 1949-1952
  - Topping, Seymour, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Watkins, Frank T., 1948
  - Webb, James E., 1950-1951
  - Wedemeyer, Lieutenant General Albert C., 1949-1950
  - Wood, C. Tyler, 1952
  - Wu, K. C., 1949-1952
  - Yen Hsi-shan, 1948
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1952
- SUBJECT FILE, 1945-1970 (Box 2-11)
  Scope and Contents note
  Memoranda, reports, printed material, correspondence, etc., arranged alphabetically by title or subject
  - Ambasade de France (Box 2)
  - American Firms in Shanghai
  - Asia
  - China
  - China Relief Mission
  - China Weekly Review
  - Collected memoranda and letters, 1945-1951
  - Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA)
    - China, 1948-1949
      - Aid Program
      - Background material
      - Chiang Kai-shek
      - Cleveland, Harlan
      - Committee meeting notes
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Doughty, C. J., Jr., Briefs and analyses of newspapers, 1948-1949
      - Financial documents
      - Greene, George M.
      - Griffin, R. Allen - Trip to Washington, D.C., January, 1949
      - Hoffman, Paul G.
      - Japan - Exports and imports
      - Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction
      - Lapham, Roger D.
        - Correspondence, press conference, speech
        - Daily schedule, (incomplete), 1948-1949
      - Li Tsung-jen
      - Office memoranda, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
      - Office reports, 1948-1949
        - China Textile Review
        - Chronological Highlights of the ECA Supply Situation During the North China Crisis
        - Final Report - Cotton Program - Tientsin
        - First Report for the Public Advisory Committee
        - Future China Aid
        - General Situation Report - Tientsin
        - Miscellaneous
        - Monthly Report, Number 1, September, 1948
        - Monthly Report, Number 2, October, 1948
        - Monthly Report, Number 3, November, 1948 (Box 5)
        - Monthly Report, Number 5, January, 1949
        - Monthly Report, Number 6, February, 1949
        - Monthly Report, Number 7, March, 1949
        - Monthly Graphic Report, December, 1948
        - Monthly Personnel Report, December, 1948
        - Monthly Status Report, February, 1949
        - Northwest China (Box 6)
        - Port Operations in China
          - December, 1948
          - February, 1949
          - March, 1949
        - Provincial governments
        - Report from the Northwest, March, 1949
        - Status of ECA Operations in Shanghai
        - Suggested Major Points for Aid-To-China Legislation
        - Summary of ECA China Aid Program, January 1949
        - Summary Statement - Extension of China Aid Program, April -December, 1949
        - Supplemental Estimate, April, 1948 -April, 1949
        - Telephone Directory, December, 1948
        - Travel orders, itineraries, etc.
        - Trip report, Nanking, December 14, 15, 1948
        - Trip report, Taiwan, May, 1949
        - West China and the ECA Program
      - Personnel
      - Price, Harry B.
      - Printed Material
        - Chinese News Service, (incomplete), 1948-1949
        - Chinese Press Review, (incomplete), 1948-1949 (Box 7)
        - Daily Translation Service, (incomplete), April -May, 1949
        - United States Information Service (USIS) - Daily News Bulletin, (incomplete), 1948-1949
        - United States Information Service (USIS) - Foreign Service News Digest, (incomplete), 1948-1949
        - Maps of China and Japan (Box 8)
        - Newspaper clippings
        - Newspaper supplements, October 10, 1948
        - Shanghai Evening Post & Mercury, (incomplete), February -March, 1949 (Box 9)
        - Miscellaneous
      - Public Advisory Committee (Box 10)
      - Reconstruction and Replacement Program
      - St. Louis, George, "Observations on Communist China,", June, 1950
      - Telephone conversation notes
    - Far East Program Division, 1950-1951
      - Committee directory
      - Correspondence
      - Office memoranda, 1950-1951
      - Office reports, 1950-1951
        - Cottage Industries, Philippines
        - Fiscal status report
        - Program operation report
        - Taiwan report
        - The Technical Assistance Program
    - Philippines
  - Eller, E. M., "United States Disaster in China,", July, 1949
  - Great Britain (Box 11)
  - Griffin, R. Allen - Biographical materials
  - Hanna, Willard A., "Bung Karno's Indonesia,", September -December, 1959
  - India
  - Indochina
  - Indonesia
  - International Conference on Agriculture and Cooperative Credit, Berkeley, California, 1952
  - Japan
  - Lear, Lieutenant General Ben
  - McCarran, Pat
  - Meng, C. Y. W., "A Chinese View of American Aid," and Moy, E. K., "A Chinese-American View of American Aid,", March, 1949
  - Miscellaneous
  - Mission to Southeast Asia, 1950
  - Mok, Poon-Kan, "Asia Today and the Western World,", 1959
  - Moyer, Raymond T., "The Economic Cooperation Administration Program in Taiwan," Address before the Chinese Association for the United Nations at Taipeh, Taiwan, March 17, 1951
  - Mutual Security Agency, 1951-1952 (Box 12)
  - South Asia professional roster, 1955
  - Southeast Asia
  - Stillman, Charles L., "Fertilizer Recommendations,", July, 1948
  - Stuart, J. Leighton
  - Taiwan
  - United States
    - Department of State
    - Technical and Economic Assistance Programs
  - Vietnam
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1948-1960 (Box 12)
  Articles and speeches by R. Allen Griffin, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - "Challenge of Southeast Asia,", 1950 (Box 12)
  - "China Changes Dynasties,", 1949
  - "The History of the 13th Infanty Regiment," (possibly written by R. Allen Griffin), 1945
  - Memorandum on the Far East prepared for Ambassador at Large, Philip C. Jessup, (with Roger D. Lapham), 1949
  - "Must Indo-China Be Lost?", 1952
  - Notes on daily activities, July -August, 1948
  - "On the Occasion of the Arrival of the 300th Shipload of Commodities for the China Aid Program,", 1949
  - Speech for Mr. Richard Bissell on Asian problems, (outline), 1951
  - Statement on departure from China, 1949
  - "United States Policy Problems in Southeast Asia," Claremont, California, 1952
  - Miscellaneous parts of speeches, notes, etc.
- PHOTOCOPIES OF DE-CLASSIFIED MATERIAL (Box 13)
  - General (Box 13)
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  General note
  See photo card catalog.
  - 19 prints of R. Allen Griffin; 1 print of R. Allen Griffin with unidentified man; 2 negatives, undated (Envelope A)
  - 1 group print of Mr. and Mrs. Roger D. Lapham, Mr. and Mrs. R. Allen Griffin and others during U.S. Economic Cooperation Administration - China Mission, 1948-1949; 3 prints of R. Allen Griffin and others signing contracts related to U.S. Economic Cooperation Administration - China, 1948-1949; 5 prints of Paul G. Hoffman's visit to China, December, 1948, including group prints with Chiang Kai-shek, Li Tsung-jen, J. Leighton Stuart and Roger D. Lapham; 1 group print of R. Allen Griffin, Henry T. Samson, Roger D. Lapham, Dr. Sun of, Lewis Clark, Wu Te-chen; 7 negatives (Envelope mB)
  - 2 miscellaneous prints, undated (Envelope C)